<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<document
        xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>OpenMM Java Wrapper Home Page</title>
        <author email="hernan-bernabe@uiowa.edu">Hernan V. Bernabe</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="OpenMM Introduction">
            <p>
                The OpenMM module contain Java Wrappers for the OpenMM API automatically generated using Jnaerator.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Generation of the Java OpenMM Wrappers using Jnaerator">
                <p>
                    Ensure that the latest version of OpenMM is installed on your machine. For example, using Anaconda
                    the command is
                </p>
                <source>conda install -c omnia openmm</source>
                <p>
                    The following Jnaerator command can then be used
                </p>
                <source>java -jar jnaerator-0.12-shaded.jar config.jnaerator</source>
                <p>
                    where the contents of "config.jnaerator" are given by
                </p>
                <source>
-limitComments

-runtime JNA

-direct

-skipDeprecated

-mode Jar

-jar openmm-7.1.1.jar

-package simtk.openmm

-library OpenMM
/Applications/anaconda3/pkgs/openmm-7.1.1-py36_0/include/OpenMMCWrapper.h

-library AmoebaOpenMM
/Applications/anaconda3/pkgs/openmm-7.1.1-py36_0/include/AmoebaOpenMMCWrapper.h
                </source>
                <p>
                    The configuration file contains the various flags needed to set up generation of the wrappers as
                    well as information about where to locate the OpenMM C header files.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Important flags include:
                    <ul>
                        <li>-runtime sets the runtime library that will be used to generate the wrapper classes,
                            in this case JNA
                        </li>
                        <li>-direct tells the JNAerator to use the fastest direct call convention
                            for library generation
                        </li>
                        <li>-skipDeprecated skips the generation of any deprecated members</li>
                        <li>-mode specifies the output mode for the JNAerator</li>
                        <li>-package sets the java package where all the generated output will reside (our package
                            is called simtk.openmm)
                        </li>
                        <li>-library sets the name of the output library. Importantly, after the library
                            flag you must specifiy (ie set the path to) where the CWrapper.h files are located. There
                            are two libraries we use to generate our wrapper classes for OpenMM.
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    For additional documentation on flags available to edit the configuration file visit the
                    <a href="https://github.com/nativelibs4java/JNAerator/wiki/Command-Line-Options-And-Environment-Variables">JNAerator Wiki.</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Environment Variable Set Up">
                <p>
                    To use the OpenMM Java wrappers, two environment variables need to be set (e.g. in .bash_profile)
                    in order to invoke the OpenMM libraries from within a Java program.
                    First, the JNA_LIBRARY_PATH variable needs to point to the location of the lib
                    subdirectory of the OpenMM installation package.
                </p>
                <source>export JNA_LIBRARY_PATH="/Applications/anaconda3/pkgs/openmm-7.1.1-py36_0/lib"</source>
                <p>
                    Second, the OPENMM_PLUGIN_DIR variable needs to point to the location of the plugins subdirectory of
                    the
                    OpenMM installation package.
                </p>
                <source>To Do.</source>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Using FFX-OpenMM">
                <p>
                    There are a number of algorithms in the FFX package that can use OpenMM under the hood if the
                    "platform" flag
                    is set to OMM. An example of this can be seen below using the Energy script:
                </p>
                <source>ffxc -Dplatform=OMM Energy yourpdb.pdb</source>
                <p>
                    where yourpdb.pdb will be replaced with the name of the pdb structure you wish to run the
                    algorithm on.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
