<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Applications</title>
    <author email="michael-schnieders@uiowa.edu">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Applications and Collaborations">
      <p>Ongoing applications of Force Field X include the following collaborations:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Understanding missense variants in the context of inherited deafness.</li>
        <li>Creation of an alchemical pipeline to predict the crystallization of pharmaceuticals.</li>
        <li>Predicting the binding affinity between cyclodextrin hosts and guest ligands.</li>
      </ul>
      <subsection name="Understanding Missense Variants in the Context of Inherited Deafness" id="missense">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              The Deafness Variation Database (DVD) provides a comprehensive guide to genetic variation in genes
              known to be associated with deafness. The DVD v9 includes all known genetic variants present in
              223 deafness-associated genes that are included on OtoSCOPE®, a comprehensive genetic deafness screening
              platform. For each of these genes that codes for a protein, Force Field X was used to refine an AlphaFold2
              structures using the AMOEBA force field and our novel global optimization algorithms. These structures are
              more consistent with the chemical features of protein structures from X-ray crystallography as assessed by
              the tool MolProbity.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <p>
                <img src="images/DVD.png" alt="DVD"/>
              </p>
              <p>The protein models are available in the DVD --
                <a href="https://deafnessvariationdatabase.org">please check them out here!</a>
              </p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <p>For more information, please see the following publication from our collaboration with labs of
                Richard J. H. Smith, Thomas Casavant and Terry Braun:
              </p>
              <p>Tollefson, M. R., Gogal, R. A., Weaver, A. M., Schaefer, A. M., Marini, R. J.,
                Azaiez, H., Kolbe, D. L., Wang, D., Weaver, A. E., Casavant, T. L., Braun, T. A.,
                Smith, R. J. H., and Schnieders, M. J.,
                Assessing Variants of Uncertain Significance Implicated in Hearing Loss Using a Comprehensive
                Deafness Proteome.
                <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00439-023-02559-9">
                  <i>Human Genetics</i>
                  <b>2023</b>, 142, 819–834.
                </a>
              </p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Alchemical Polymorph Prediction Pipeline" id="polymorph">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>We are collaborating with Mitsubishi Tanabe Pharma and Takeda to create a complete crystal structure
              prediction pipeline using Force Field X.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <img src="images/Polymorphs.png" alt="Polymorph"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <p>Please see our recent joint publication describing the "Progressive Alignment of Crystals" (PAC)
                algorithm:
              </p>
              <p>
                Nessler, A. J., Okada, O., Hermon, M. J., Nagata, H., and Schnieders, M. J.,
                Progressive Alignment of Crystals: Reproducible and Efficient Assessment of Crystal Structure
                Similarity.
                <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S1600576722009670">
                  <i>Journal of Applied Crystallography</i>
                  <b>2022</b>, 55, 1528-1537.
                </a>
              </p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Cyclodextrin Host-Guest Binding Affinity">
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>This is a new collaboration with Pfizer -- more soon on our progress.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <img src="images/cyclodextrin.png" alt="Cyclodextrin"/>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
