<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document
  xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Optimization and Sampling Commands</title>
    <author email="michael-schnieders@uiowa.edu">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Optimization and Sampling Commands">
      <p>Local and Global Minimization, Dynamics, Clustering, Superposition and Alchemical Free Energy Simulations.</p>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Command</th>
            <th>Purpose</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Anneal.html">Anneal</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Anneal command runs simulated annealing to optimize a structure.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/BAR.html">BAR</a>
            </td>
            <td>The BAR command evaluates a free energy difference using the Bennett Acceptance Ratio
              algorithm based on archives of snapshots.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Cluster.html">Cluster</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Cluster command clusters structures utilizing RMSD.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Dynamics.html">Dynamics</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Dynamics command implements molecular and stochastic dynamics algorithms.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/ForEachFile.html">ForEachFile</a>
            </td>
            <td>The ForEachFile command runs another command (i.e., Energy or Minimize) on a series
              of files with support for MPI parallelization across nodes.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Histogram.html">Histogram</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Histogram command prints out an Orthogonal Space Tempering histogram using an
              input structure and histogram (*.his) file.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/ManyBody.html">ManyBody</a>
            </td>
            <td>The ManyBody command performs a discrete optimization using a many-body energy
              expansion and elimination expressions.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Minimize.html">Minimize</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Minimize command uses a limited-memory BFGS algorithm to minimize the energy of a
              molecular system.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/MinimizeCrystals.html">MinimizeCrystals</a>
            </td>
            <td>The MinimizeCrystals command uses a limited-memory BFGS algorithm to minimize the
              energy of a crystal, including both coordinates and/or unit cell parameters.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/MinimizeOpenMM.html">MinimizeOpenMM</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Minimize command uses an OpenMM accelerated L-BFGS algorithm to minimize the
              energy of a molecular system.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/MutatePDB.html">MutatePDB</a>
            </td>
            <td>The MutatePDB command mutates a residue of a PDB file.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Scheduler.html">Scheduler</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Scheduler command runs a Parallel Java job scheduler on a cluster with multiple
              nodes.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/SortArc.html">SortArc</a>
            </td>
            <td>The SortArc command sorts archive file snapshots from Monte Carlo Thermodynamics jobs
              by lambda value.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Superpose.html">Superpose</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Superpose command superposes molecules form an ARC or multiple model PDB file
              (all v. all or one v. all) or between two PDB/XYZ files.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/SuperposeCrystals.html">SuperposeCrystals</a>
            </td>
            <td>The SuperposeCrystals command quantifies the similarity of input crystals based on a
              novel progressive alignment approach.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="commands/Thermodynamics.html">Thermodynamics</a>
            </td>
            <td>The Thermodynamics command computes free energy differences using orthogonal space
              tempering or via windowed approaches.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
