<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<document
        xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <author email="michael-schnieders@uiowa.edu">
            Michael J. Schnieders
        </author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Welcome to the Force Field X Home Page">
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <td>
                        <h4>Introduction</h4>
                        <p>Force Field X is an atomic resolution molecular modeling application that targets open
                            research questions in the areas of:
                        </p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>predicting the structure, thermodynamic stability and solubility of organic polymer
                                crystals,
                            </li>
                            <li>predicting the effect of missense mutations on protein structure, thermodynamics and
                                molecular phenotype
                            </li>
                            <li>computational design of biomolecules in both soluble and crystalline environments</li>
                        </ul>
                        <h4>New Approaches Developed in the Schnieders' Lab</h4>
                        <p>To address these questions, novel global optimization methods and alchemical thermodynamic
                            paths
                            have been implemented in Force Field X. Examples include:
                        </p>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Organic crystals property prediction based on
                                "Growth of the Asymmetric Unit into a Crystal via alcHEmy" (GAUCHE)
                            </li>
                            <li>Many-body dead-end elimination (MB-DEE) for global optimization of non-pairwise energy
                                functions over a discrete permutation space (i.e. side-chain rotamers).
                            </li>
                            <li>A general "dual force field" framework to compute the thermodynamic cost to change
                                between
                                fixed charge (i.e. OPLS-AA or Amber) and a polarizable multipole force field (i.e.
                                AMOEBA).
                            </li>
                            <li>Refinement of biomolecular structures against experimental data sets (i.e. X-ray /
                                neutron diffraction
                                and/or CryoEM) and the polarizable AMOEBA force field.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                        <h4>The Force Field X Code and Manual</h4>
                        <p>
                            The FFX code is parallelized for clusters of many-core nodes using an open (GPL v. 3),
                            modular and platform independent approach. See the FFX online manual for instructions on how
                            to
                            <a href="download.html">download</a>
                            and
                            <a href="install.html">install</a>
                            the program.
                            The manual also describes available
                            <a href="commands.html">modeling commands</a>
                            and
                            <a href="properties.html">property settings</a>,
                            and provides a few <a href="examples.html">examples</a> with more on the way.
                        </p>
                    </td>
                    <td bgcolor="white">
                        <p align="left">
                            <img src="images/rotamer.png" alt="Rotamer"/>
                        </p>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <!-- tr>
                    <td>
                        <h4>Development</h4>
                        <p>Contribute to Force Field X by learning how to clone the
                            <a href="source.html">code</a> from GitHub and then build it.
                            We also provide instructions for how to use its
                            <a href="modules.html">modules</a> in your own programs.
                        </p>
                        <script type="text/javascript" src="js/factoids.js"></script>
                    </td>
                </tr -->
            </table>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
