<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document
    xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Properties</title>
        <author email="michael.schnieders@gmail.com">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Properties">
            <subsection name="Unit Cell and Space Group Properties">
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property</th>
                            <th>Type</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>  
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>a-axis</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Length of the a-axis of the unit cell in Angstroms.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>b-axis</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Length of the b-axis of the unit cell in Angstroms.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>c-axis</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Length of the c-axis of the unit cell in Angstroms.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>alpha</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Angle between the b-axis and c-axis of the unit cell in degrees.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>beta</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Angle between the a-axis and c-axis of the unit cell in degrees.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>gamma</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Angle between the a-axis and b-axis of the unit cell in degrees.</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>spacegroup</td>
                            <td>string</td>
                            <td>One of the 230 space groups. The defaut is "P1" if an a-axis is
                            specified, but not the space group. Internal checks are performed
                            to make certain the unit cell parameters are consistent with
                            the symmetry of the space group.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="AMOEBA Force Field Properties">
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property</th>
                            <th>Type</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>mpoleterm</td>
                            <td>boolean</td>
                            <td>Controls use of the permanent multipole term for
                            the AMOEBA potential. The default is true. Setting
                            mpoleterm to false also turns off polarization, overriding
                            the polarizeterm property below.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>polarizeterm</td>
                            <td>boolean</td>
                            <td>Controls use of the polarization term for the AMOEBA
                            potential. The default is true. Setting polarizeterm to
                            false overrides the polarization property below.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>polarization</td>
                            <td>string</td>
                            <td>[mutual/direct/none] The default is mutual, 
                        which indicates the induced dipoles on each atom interact 
                        self-consistently. Direct indicates that induced dipoles are
                        influenced by the permanent multipoles, but not each other. None
                        turns off polarization
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>polar-eps</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>This is the convergence criteria for the self-consistent field
                        calculation in units of RMS Debye. The default is 1e-6, which is 
                        appropriate for optimizations to tight tolerance. For optimization
                        during X-rey refinement to an RMS gradient per atom of 0.1, then
                        a looser polar-eps of 1e-3 is sufficient. For molecular dynamics
                        with a thermostat, 1e-2 is resonable trade-off between accuracy
                        and performance.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>polar-sor</td>
                            <td>double</td>
                            <td>Calculation of the self-consistent field is based on successive
                        over-relaxtion (SOR). The polar-sor parameter controls the fractional
                        change in the induced dipoles that is accepted prior to the beginning
                        of the following iteration. The default value is 0.70, although
                        in some cases a slightly more conservative value of 0.65 is necessary.
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Particle-mesh Ewald Properties">
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property</th>
                            <th>Type</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>  
                    <tbody>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
