<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document
    xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Properties</title>
        <author email="michael-schnieders@uiowa.edu">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Property Overview">
            <p>Force Field X <b>properties</b> are defined using the following precedence order:
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li>Highest precedence is given to the Java system properties mechanism:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <code>-Dkey=value</code> from the Force Field X command line
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Equivalently, use the following code within a script
                            <b>before</b> the structure file is opened.
                            <source>System.setProperty("key","value")</source>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Second highest precedence is given to structure specific properties.
                    For example, when opening a structure named filename.pdb or filename.xyz,
                    Force Field X will attempt to read properties from:
                    <ol>
                        <li>fileame.properties
                        </li>
                        <li>filename.key (only if fileame.properties is not found)
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <li>
                    User specific properties from the file
                    <code>~/.ffx/ffx.properties</code>.
                </li>
                <li>Properties in the file defined by the environment variable
                    <code>FFX_PROPERTIES</code>
                </li>
                <li>
                    Finally, properties are read in from force field definition
                    files that are stored internally by Force Field X.
                </li>
            </ol>
            <subsection name="Property Groups">
                <p>Force Field X properties are grouped into the following categories:</p>
                <table>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Property Group</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <p>
                                    <a href="properties-forcefield.html">Force Field</a>
                                </p>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <p>Specify the functional form of the force field, including bonded terms, van der Waals and electrostatics.</p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <p>
                                    <a href="properties-pme.html">Particle Mesh Ewald Electrostatics</a>
                                </p>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <p>Define PME electrostatics parameters such as real space cutoff, interpolation order and mesh density.</p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <p>
                                    <a href="properties-refine.html">X-ray, Neutron and Real Space Refinement</a>
                                </p>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <p>Control details of structural refinement against experimental data sets and advanced force fields.</p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <p>
                                    <a href="properties-spacegroup.html">Unit Cell, Space Group and Periodic Boundary Conditions</a>
                                </p>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <p>Define the size of the simulation cell, spece group symmetry and use of PBC.</p>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
