<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Selected Publications</title>
    <author email="michael-schnieders@uiowa.edu">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Selected Recent Publications with Force Field X">
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Year</th>
          <th>Publication</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2023</b>
          </td>
          <td>
            Thiel, A., Speranza, M., Jadhav, S., Stevens, L., Unruh, D., Ren, P., Ponder, J., Shen, J. and Schnieders, M.
            Constant-pH Simulations with the Polarizable Atomic Multipole AMOEBA Force Field
            <a href="https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2023-96z34">
              <i>ChemRxiv. Cambridge: Cambridge Open Engage</i>
              <b>2023</b>
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --></td>
          <td>Corrigan, R. A., Thiel, A. C., Lynn, J. R., Casavant, T. L., Ren, P., Ponder, J. W., and Schnieders, M.
            J.,
            A Generalized Kirkwood Implicit Solvent for the Polarizable AMOEBA Protein Model.
            <a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0158914">
              <i>Journal of Chemical Physics</i>
              <b>2023</b>, 159, 054102.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --></td>
          <td>
            Tollefson, M. R., Gogal, R. A., Weaver, A. M., Schaefer, A. M., Marini, R. J.,
            Azaiez, H., Kolbe, D. L., Wang, D., Weaver, A. E., Casavant, T. L., Braun, T. A.,
            Smith, R. J. H., and Schnieders, M. J.,
            Assessing Variants of Uncertain Significance Implicated in Hearing Loss Using a Comprehensive
            Deafness Proteome.
            <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00439-023-02559-9">
              <i>Human Genetics</i>
              <b>2023</b>, 142, 819–834.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2022</b>
          </td>
          <td>Nessler, A. J., Okada, O., Hermon, M. J., Nagata, H., and Schnieders, M. J.,
            Progressive Alignment of Crystals: Reproducible and Efficient Assessment of Crystal Structure Similarity.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S1600576722009670">
              <i>Journal of Applied Crystallography</i>
              <b>2022</b>, 55, 1528-1537.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --></td>
          <td>Dybeck, E. C., Thiel, A., Schnieders, M. J., Pickard, F. C. I. V., Wood, G. P. F.,
            Krzyzaniak, J. F., and Hancock, B. C.,
            A Comparison of Methods for Computing Relative Anhydrous–Hydrate Stability
            with Molecular Simulation,
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.cgd.2c00832">
              <i>Crystal Growth and Design</i>
              <b>2022</b>, 23, 142-167.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2021</b>
          </td>
          <td>Corrigan, R. A., Qi, G., Thiel, A. C., Lynn, J. R., Walker, B. D., Casavant, T. L.,
            Lagardere, L., Piquemal, J.-P., Ponder, J. W., Ren, P., and Schnieders, M. J.,
            Implicit Solvents for the Polarizable Atomic Multipole AMOEBA Force Field.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.0c01286">
              <i>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</i>
              <b>2021</b>, 17 (4), 2323-2341.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2019</b>
          </td>
          <td>
            Tollefson, M. R., Litman, J. M., Qi, G., O’Connell, C. E., Wipfler, M. J.,
            Marini, R. J., Bernabe, H. V., Tollefson, W. T. A., Braun, T. A., Casavant, T. L.,
            Smith, R. J. H. and M. J. Schnieders,
            Structural Insights into Hearing Loss Genetics from Polarizable Protein Repacking.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2019.06.030">
              <i>Biophysical Journal</i>
              <b>2019</b>, 117 (3), 602-612.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --> </td>
          <td>Litman, J. M., Thiel, A. C., and M. J. Schnieders,
            Scalable Indirect Free Energy Method Applied to Divalent Cation-Metalloprotein Binding.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.9b00147">
              <i>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</i>
              <b>2019</b>, 15 (8), 4602-4614.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2016</b>
          </td>
          <td>Nessler, I. J., Litman, J. M., and M. J. Schnieders,
            Toward Polarizable AMOEBA Thermodynamics at Fixed Charge Efficiency Using a Dual Force Field Approach.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C6CP02595A">
              <i>Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics</i>
              <b>2016</b>, 18 (44), 30313-30322.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --></td>
          <td>
            Bell, D., Qi, R., Jing, Z., Xiang, J. Y., Mejias, C., Schnieders, M., Ponder, J., and P. Ren,
            Calculating binding free energies of host-guest systems using AMOEBA polarizable force field.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1039/C6CP02509A">
              <i>Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics</i>
              <b>2016</b>, 18 (44), 30261-30269.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2015</b>
          </td>
          <td>
            LuCore, S. D., Litman, J. M., Powers, K. T., Gao, S., Lynn, A. M., Tollefson, W. T. A., Fenn, T. D.,
            Washington, M. T. and M. J. Schnieders,
            Dead-End Elimination with a Polarizable Force Field Repacks PCNA Models.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2015.06.062">
              <i>Biophysical Journal</i>
              <b>2015</b>, 109 (4), 816-826.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><!-- BLANK --></td>
          <td>Shi, Y., Schnieders, M. J., Piquemal, J.-P., and P. Ren,
            Polarizable Force Fields for Biomolecular Modeling.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1002/9781118889886.ch2">
              <i>Reviews in Computational Chemistry</i>
              <b>2015</b>
              Edition: 28, Publisher: Springer, Editors: Kenny B. Lipkowitz
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>
            <b>2014</b>
          </td>
          <td>Park, J., Nessler, I., McClain, B., Macikenas D., Baltrusaitis, J. and M. J. Schnieders,
            Absolute Organic Crystal Thermodynamics: Growth of the Asymmetric Unit into a Crystal via Alchemy.
            <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ct500180m">
              <i>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</i>
              <b>2014</b>
              10, (7), 2781-2791.
            </a>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
