<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document
    xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0
    http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Publications</title>
        <author email="michael.schnieders@gmail.com">Michael J. Schnieders</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Publications">
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Link</th>
                        <th>Publication</th>
                        <th>Module</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="white">
                            <font color="blue">
                                <b>2011</b>
                            </font>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                        </td>
                        <td>Fenn, T. D. and M. J. Schnieders, Polarizable Atomic Multipole X-Ray Refinement: Weighting Schemes for Macromolecular Diffraction
                            <i>Acta Crystallographica Section D</i>
                            <b>2011</b> (accepted).
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            In the past, weighting between the sum of chemical and data-based targets in macro-
                            molecular crystallographic refinement was based on comparing the gradients or Hes-
                            sian diagonal terms of the two potential functions. Here we demonstrate limitations of
                            this scheme, especially in the context of a maximum likelihood target that is inherently
                            weighted by the model and data errors. In fact, the congruence between the maximum
                            likelihood target and a chemical potential based on polarizable atomic multipole elec-
                            trostatics evaluated with Ewald summation has opened the door to a transferable,
                            static weight. We derive from first principles an optimal static weight and demon-
                            strate that it is transferable across a broad range of data resolutions in the context
                            of our recent implementation of X-ray crystallographic refinement using the polariz-
                            able AMOEBA force field and show the resulting models are balanced with respect
                            to optimizing both Rfree and Molprobity scores. Conversely, the classical automatic
                            weighting scheme is shown to lead to under or overfitting of the data and poor model geometry. 
                            We also highlight the benefits of this approach for low resolution diffraction
                            data, where the need for prior chemical information is of particular importance. We
                            demonstrate that this method is transferable between low and high resolution maxi-
                            mum likelihood based crystallographic refinement, which proves for the first time that
                            resolution dependent parameterization of either the weight or chemical potential is
                            unnecessary.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                            <br/>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.str.2011.01.015">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Fenn, T. D.; Schnieders, M. J.; Mustyakimov, M.; Wu, C.; Pande, V. S.; Langan, P.; Brunger, A. T., Reintroducing electrostatics into macromolecular crystallographic refinement: application to neutron crystallography and DNA hydration.
                            <i>Structure</i>
                            <b>2011</b> 19, (4), 523-533.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Most current crystallographic structure refinements augment the diffraction data
                            with a priori information consisting of bond, angle, dihedral, planarity 
                            restraints, and atomic repulsion based on the Pauli exclusion principle. Yet, 
                            electrostatics and van der Waals attraction are physical forces that provide 
                            additional a priori information. Here, we assess the inclusion of electrostatics 
                            for the force field used for all-atom (including hydrogen) joint neutron/X-ray 
                            refinement. Two DNA and a protein crystal structure were refined against joint 
                            neutron/X-ray diffraction data sets using force fields without electrostatics or 
                            with electrostatics. Hydrogen-bond orientation/geometry favors the inclusion of 
                            electrostatics. Refinement of Z-DNA with electrostatics leads to a hypothesis 
                            for the entropic stabilization of Z-DNA that may partly explain the 
                            thermodynamics of converting the B form of DNA to its Z form. Thus, inclusion of 
                            electrostatics assists joint neutron/X-ray refinements, especially for placing 
                            and orienting hydrogen atoms.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                            <br/>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ct100506d">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            Schnieders, M. J.; Fenn, T. D.; Pande, V. S., Polarizable atomic multipole X-ray refinement: particle-mesh Ewald electrostatics for macromolecular crystals.
                            <i>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</i>
                            <b>2011</b> 7, (4), 1141-1156.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Refinement of macromolecular models from X-ray crystallography experiments 
                            benefits from prior chemical knowledge at all resolutions. As the quality of 
                            the prior chemical knowledge from quantum or classical molecular physics 
                            improves, in principle so will resulting structural models. Due to limitations 
                            in computer performance and electrostatic algorithms, commonly used 
                            macromolecules X-ray crystallography refinement protocols have had limited 
                            support for rigorous molecular physics in the past. For example, electrostatics 
                            is often neglected in favor of nonbonded interactions based on a purely repulsive
                            van der Waals potential. In this work we present advanced algorithms for desktop
                            workstations that open the door to X-ray refinement of even the most challenging 
                            macromolecular data sets using state-of-the-art classical molecular physics. 
                            First we describe theory for particle mesh Ewald (PME) summation that 
                            consistently handles the symmetry of all 230 space groups, replicates of the 
                            unit cell such that the minimum image convention can be used with a real space 
                            cutoff of any size and the combination of space group symmetry with replicates. 
                            An implementation of symmetry accelerated PME for the polarizable atomic 
                            multipole optimized energetics for biomolecular applications (AMOEBA) force 
                            field is presented. Relative to a single CPU core performing calculations on a 
                            P1 unit cell, our AMOEBA engine called Force Field X (FFX) accelerates energy 
                            evaluations by more than a factor of 24 on an 8-core workstation with a Tesla 
                            GPU coprocessor for 30 structures that contain 240000 atoms on average in the 
                            unit cell. The benefit of AMOEBA electrostatics evaluated with PME for 
                            macromolecular X-ray crystallography refinement is demonstrated via rerefinement 
                            of 10 crystallographic data sets that range in resolution from 1.7 to 4.5 Å. 
                            Beginning from structures obtained by local optimization without electrostatics, 
                            further optimization using AMOEBA with PME electrostatics improved agreement of 
                            the model with the data (Rfree was lowered by 0.5%), improved geometric features 
                            such as favorable (, ψ) backbone conformations, and lowered the average potential 
                            energy per residue by over 10 kcal/mol. Furthermore, the MolProbity structure validation 
                            tool indicates that the geometry of these rerefined structures is consistent with X-ray 
                            crystallographic data collected up to 2.2 Å, which is 0.9 Å better than the actual mean 
                            quality (3.1 Å). We conclude that polarizable AMOEBA-assisted X-ray refinement offers 
                            advantages to methods that neglect electrostatics and is now efficient enough for routine 
                            use.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                            <br/>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="white">
                            <font color="blue">
                                <b>2010</b>
                            </font>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a target="_blank" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2010.02.057">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Fenn, T. D.*; Schnieders, M. J.*; Brunger, A. T.; Pande, V. S., Polarizable atomic multipole X-ray refinement: hydration geometry and application to macromolecules.
                            <i>Biophysical Journal</i>
                            <b>2010</b>, 98, (12), 2984-2992. (* joint first authors)
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            We recently developed a polarizable atomic multipole refinement method assisted 
                            by the AMOEBA force field for macromolecular crystallography. Compared to 
                            standard refinement procedures, the method uses a more rigorous treatment of 
                            X-ray scattering and electrostatics that can significantly improve the resultant 
                            information contained in an atomic model. We applied this method to 
                            high-resolution lysozyme and trypsin data sets, and validated its utility for 
                            precisely describing biomolecular electron density, as indicated by a 0.4–0.6% 
                            decrease in the R- and Rfree-values, and a corresponding decrease in the 
                            relative energy of 0.4–0.8 Kcal/mol/residue. The re-refinements illustrate the 
                            ability of force-field electrostatics to orient water networks and catalytically 
                            relevant hydrogens, which can be used to make predictions regarding active site 
                            function, activity, and protein-ligand interaction energies. Re-refinement of a 
                            DNA crystal structure generates the zigzag spine pattern of hydrogen bonding in 
                            the minor groove without manual intervention. The polarizable atomic multipole 
                            electrostatics model implemented in the AMOEBA force field is applicable and 
                            informative for crystal structures solved at any resolution.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a target="_blank" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S0907444910031045">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Fenn, T. D.; Schnieders, M. J.; Brunger, A. T., A smooth and differentiable bulk-solvent model for macromolecular diffraction.
                            <i>Acta Crystallographica Section D</i>
                            <b>2010</b>, 66, (9), 1024-1031.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Inclusion of low-resolution data in macromolecular crystallography requires a 
                            model for the bulk solvent. Previous methods have used a binary mask to 
                            accomplish this, which has proven to be very effective, but the mask is 
                            discontinuous at the solute–solvent boundary (i.e. the mask value jumps from 
                            zero to one) and is not differentiable with respect to atomic parameters. 
                            Here, two algorithms are introduced for com­puting bulk-solvent models using 
                            either a polynomial switch or a smoothly thresholded product of Gaussians, 
                            and both models are shown to be efficient and differentiable with respect to 
                            atomic coordinates. These alternative bulk-solvent models offer algorithmic 
                            improvements, while showing similar agreement of the model with the observed 
                            amplitudes relative to the binary model as monitored using R, R free and 
                            differences between experimental and model phases. As with the standard solvent 
                            models, the alternative models improve the agreement primarily with lower 
                            resolution (>6 Å) data versus no bulk solvent. The models are easily implemented 
                            into crystallographic software packages and can be used as a general method for 
                            bulk-solvent correction in macromolecular crystallography.
                            \[\textbf{F}_{{t}}=\textbf{F}_{{c}}-k_{{s}}\textbf{F}_{{m}}{{\rm e}^{-1/4\,B_{{s}}\left|\textbf{s}\right|^{2}}}\]
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a target="_blank" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/jp910674d">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            Ponder, J. W.; Wu, C.; Ren, P.; Pande, V. S.; Chodera, J. D.; Schnieders, M. J.; Haque, I.; Mobley, D. L.; Lambrecht, D. S.; DiStasio, R. A.; Head-Gordon, M.; Clark, G. N. I.; Johnson, M. E.; Head-Gordon, T., Current Status of the AMOEBA Polarizable Force Field.
                            <i>The Journal of Physical Chemistry B.</i>
                            <b>2010</b>, 114, 2549-2564.
                            <br/>
                            Molecular force fields have been approaching a generational transition over the 
                            past several years, moving away from well-established and well-tuned, but 
                            intrinsically limited, fixed point charge models toward more intricate and 
                            expensive polarizable models that should allow more accurate description of 
                            molecular properties. The recently introduced AMOEBA force field is a leading 
                            publicly available example of this next generation of theoretical model, but to 
                            date, it has only received relatively limited validation, which we address here. 
                            We show that the AMOEBA force field is in fact a significant improvement over 
                            fixed charge models for small molecule structural and thermodynamic observables 
                            in particular, although further fine-tuning is necessary to describe solvation 
                            free energies of drug-like small molecules, dynamical properties away from 
                            ambient conditions, and possible improvements in aromatic interactions. State of 
                            the art electronic structure calculations reveal generally very good agreement 
                            with AMOEBA for demanding problems such as relative conformational energies of 
                            the alanine tetrapeptide and isomers of water sulfate complexes. AMOEBA is shown 
                            to be especially successful on protein−ligand binding and computational X-ray 
                            crystallography where polarization and accurate electrostatics are critical.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="white">
                            <font color="blue">
                                <b>2009</b>
                            </font>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1107/S0907444909022707" target="_blank">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Schnieders, M. J.; Fenn, T. D.; Pande, V. S.; Brunger, A. T., Polarizable atomic multipole X-ray refinement: application to peptide crystals,
                            <i>Acta Crystallographica Section D</i>
                            <b>2009</b>, 65, (9), 952-965.
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/xray/index.html">X-Ray Refinement</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/IEMBS.2009.5335108" target="_blank">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Yue, S.; Dian, J.; Schnieders, M. J.; Ren, P. In
                            <i>Trypsin-ligand binding free energy calculation with AMOEBA</i>,
                            Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society. EMBC. Annual International Conference of the IEEE, 2009; 2009; pp 2328-2331.
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/binding/index.html">Binding Affinity</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jcc.21268" target="_blank">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            Jiao, D.; Zhang, J. J.; Duke, R. E.; Li, G. H.; Schnieders, M. J.; Ren, P. Y., Trypsin-Ligand Binding Free Energies from Explicit and Implicit Solvent Simulations with Polarizable Potential.
                            <i>Journal of Computational Chemistry</i>
                            <b>2009</b>, 30, (11), 1701-1711.
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/binding/index.html">Binding Affinity</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="white">
                            <font color="blue">
                                <b>2008</b>
                            </font>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0711686105" target="_blank">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Jiao, D.; Golubkov, P. A.; Darden, T. A.; Ren, P., Calculation of protein-ligand binding free energy by using a polarizable potential.
                            <i>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</i>
                            <b>2008</b>, 105, (17), 6290-6295.
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/binding/index.html">Binding Affinity</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="white">
                            <font color="blue">
                                <b>2007</b>
                            </font>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a target="_blank" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1021/ct7001336">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Schnieders, M. J.; Ponder, J. W., Polarizable Atomic Multipole Solutes in a Generalized Kirkwood Continuum.
                            <i>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</i>
                            <b>2007</b>, 3, (6), 2083-2097.
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>
                            <a target="_blank" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2714528">
                                <img src="images/pdf.png" alt="PDF"/>
                            </a>
                        </td>
                        <td>Schnieders, M. J.; Baker, N. A.; Ren, P.; Ponder, J. W., Polarizable atomic multipole solutes in a Poisson-Boltzmann continuum.
                            <i>Journal of Chemical Physics</i>
                            <b>2007</b>, 126, (12).
                        </td>
                        <td>
                            <a href="modules/potentials/index.html">Potentials</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
