<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document
    xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Source Code</title>
        <author email="schnied@stanford.edu">Michael Schnieders</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Source Code">
            <p>"<i>A (molecular biophysics) algorithm must be seen to be believed</i>." Donald Knuth</p>
            <subsection name="Git the Code">
                <p>The Force Field X project is hosted at <a href="http://www.kenai.com/projects/ffx/">Kenai</a>with the source code in a GIT repository.
                    "<a href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a>is a free and open source, distributed version control system designed to handle everything from
                    small to very large projects with speed and efficiency."
                    To clone the Force Field X source first join the Kenai site, set up an ssh key and then join the FFX project. The GIT command is:
                    <source>git clone ssh://KENAI.USER.NAME@git.kenai.com/ffx~source ffx</source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Building Force Field X">
                <p>A Maven project file (pom.xml) is provided to build Force Field X on any platform. After cloing the Force Field X git repository, change
                    directoies into the base project directory. Then execute:
                    <source>mvn deploy</source>
                    This requires Maven v. 2.2.1 or later to be installed with its bin directory included in your $PATH environment variable. The first time this command
                    is executed, Maven will download build dependencies and Force Field X runtime dependecies. Future executions are quicker. Force Field X will self-test
                    its modules and report failures. Only code that passes all testing should be uploaded to the Kenai repository, so if any test fails it may be
                    due to a local configuration issue.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once the build succeeds, Force Field X can be executed using platform dependent start-up scripts located in the bin/PLATFORM directories, where PLATFORM
                    is either macosx, linux or windows.
                    <source>bin/linux/ffxc scripts/energy.ffx</source>
                    The appropriate directory for your operating system may be appended to your $PATH environment variable.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Developing Force Field X">
            <subsection name="Maven">
                <p>The Force Field X web site facilitates technology transfer and further development of features and is built with Maven.
                The Application Programming Interface (API) documentation for Force Field X packages is available as <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadocs.</a>
                The Force Field X source code is available fully <a href="xref/index.html">cross-referenced </a>with line numbers.
                For detailed information on the layout of the Force Field X source code visit the "Project Documentation" area of this website.
                For example, we use the <a href="jdepend-report.html">JDepend Report</a> to avoid cyclic package dependencies.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="NetBeans">

            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Kenai.com / Java.net">

            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
