<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document
    xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Source Code</title>
        <author email="michael.schnieders@gmail.com">Michael Schnieders</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Source Code">
            <subsection name="Git the Code">
                <p>The Force Field X project is hosted at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.kenai.com/projects/ffx/">Kenai</a> with the source code in a GIT repository.
                    "<a target="_blank" href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a> is a free and open source, distributed version control system designed to handle everything from
                    small to very large projects with speed and efficiency."
                    To clone the Force Field X source using GIT:
                    <source>git clone git://kenai.com/ffx~source ffx</source>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Building Force Field X">
                <p>A Maven project file (pom.xml) is provided to build Force Field X on any platform. After cloing the Force Field X git repository, change
                    directoies into the base project directory. Then execute:
                    <source>mvn deploy</source>
                    This requires Maven v. 3.0.2 or later to be installed with its bin directory included in your $PATH environment variable. The first time this command
                    is executed, Maven will download build dependencies and Force Field X runtime dependecies. Future executions are quicker. Force Field X will self-test
                    its modules and report failures. Only code that passes all testing should be uploaded to the Kenai repository, so if any test fails it may be
                    due to a local configuration issue. To skip the tests:
                    <source>mvn -DskipTests deploy</source>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Once the build succeeds, Force Field X can be executed using platform dependent start-up scripts located in the bin.
                    On Mac OS X or Linux:
                    <source>bin/ffxc energy examples/alamet.xyz</source>
                    On Windows:
                    <source>bin/ffxc.bat energy examples/alamet.xyz</source>
                    The ffx/bin directory should be appended to your $PATH environment variable. The "energy" command
                    refers to an internal version of the energy.ffx script that can be found in the ffx/scripts
                    directory. To embed your own script within FFX, place it into the scripts directory and
                    rebuild FFX.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Developing Force Field X">
            <subsection name="Maven Software Project Management">
                <p>Maven is like "make", but exceptionally more powerful due to the platform independence of the Jave Runtime Environment.
                Maven is used to manage the dependencies of Force Field X, compile it, test it, document it and then put everything together into the website.</p>
                <p>The Force Field X web site facilitates technology transfer and further development of features. Available documentation includes:</p>
                <ul><li>Application Programming Interface (API) documentation for Force Field X packages is available as <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadocs.</a></li>
                    <li>Force Field X source code is available <a href="xref/index.html">cross-referenced</a> with line numbers.</li>
                    <li>The <a href="jdepend-report.html">JDepend Report</a> is used to avoid cyclic package dependencies.</li>
                </ul>
                <p>For more information on the layout of the Force Field X project visit the "Project Documentation" area of this website.</p>
            </subsection>
            <!-- subsection name="Kenai.com / Java.net">
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="NetBeans Integrated Development Environment (IDE)">
            </subsection -->
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
